PEDRO HESPANHOL

1154A Hearst Avenue & Berkeley, CA 94702 & 510-944-4982

http://pedrohespanhol.com pedrohespanhol@berkeley.edu

PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

My research is focused on the interplay between control, learning and optimization, with emphasis on autonomous systems applications and multi-agent systems. I have work experience with software development of embedded algorithms for real-time applications, including nonlinear, hybrid, and stochastic systems. I am also interested in all aspects of computational optimization, from modeling techniques to state-of-the-art practical implementations. My current research interests include: real-time optimal control, learning and control, and algorithmic mechanism design.

CURRRENT POSITION

PhD Student, Industrial Engineering and Operations Research, UC Berkeley

EDUCATION

PhD, Industrial Engineering and Operations Research, UC Berkeley, 2020

Minors: Statistics and Economics

Advisor: Anil Aswani

MS, Industrial Engineering and Operation Research, UC Berkeley, 2016

BS, Industrial Engineering, Pontifical Catholic University Of Rio De Janeiro, 2014

Minor: Risk Analysis

RESEARCH AREAS AND COURSEWORK

Optimization Theory and Optimal Control

Math Programming I & II, Computational Optimization, Graph Algorithms and Network Flows, Predictive Control, Learning and Optimization, Applied Dynamic Programming

Statistical Learning and Deep Learning

Statistical Learning Theory, Deep Time-Series Learning, Deep Reinforcement Learning

Game Theory and Mechanism Design

Microeconomics and Game Theory, Mechanism Design and Agency Theory

Financial Engineering and Stochastic Processes

Financial Engineering I & II, Stochastic Processes I & II

JOURNAL PUBLICATIONS

Sensor Switching Control Under Attacks Detectable by Finite Sample Dynamic Watermarking Tests

Pedro Hespanhol, Matthew Porter, Ram Vasudevan, and Anil Aswani

Submitted to IEEE Transactions on Automatic Control, under 2nd round of review (2020)

preprint: https://arxiv.org/abs/1909.00014

Statistical Consistency of Set-Membership Estimator for Linear Systems

Pedro Hespanhol and Anil Aswani

IEEE Control Systems Letters (2020)

https://doi.org/10.1109/LCSYS.2020.2990998

Detecting Generalized Replay Attacks via Time-Varying Dynamic Watermarking

Matthew Porter, Pedro Hespanhol, Anil Aswani, Matthew Johnson-Roberson, and Ram Vasudevan Submitted to *IEEE Transactions on Automatic Control*, under 2nd round of review (2020)

preprint: https://arxiv.org/abs/1909.08111

Adjoint-Based SQP Method with Block-Qise Quasi-Newton Jacobian Updates for Nonlinear Optimal Control

Pedro Hespanhol and Rien Quirynen

Optimization Methods and Software (2019)

https://doi.org/10.1080/10556788.2019.1653869

CONFERENCE PAPERS

Hypothesis Testing Approach to Detecting Collusion in Competitive Environments

Pedro Hespanhol and Anil Aswani

In Proceedings of International Conference on Performance Evaluation Methodologies and Tools (Valuetools), to appear (2020)

preprint: https://arxiv.org/abs/2003.09967

Detecting Deception Attacks on Autonomous Vehicles via Linear Time-Varying Dynamic Watermarking

Matthew Porter, Sidhartha Dey, Arnav Joshi, Pedro Hespanhol, Anil Aswani, Matthew Johnson-Roberson, and Ram Vasudevan

In Proceedings of Conference on Control Technology and Applications (CCTA), to appear (2020)

preprint: https://arxiv.org/abs/2001.09859

Surrogate Optimal Control for Strategic Multi-Agent Systems

Pedro Hespanhol and Anil Aswani

In Proceedings of Conference on Decision and Control (CDC) (2019)

https://doi.org/10.1109/CDC40024.2019.9029475

A Structure Exploiting Branch-and-Bound Algorithm for Mixed-Integer Model Predictive Control

Pedro Hespanhol, Rien Quirynen, and Stefano Di Cairano

In Proceedings of European Control Conference (ECC) (2019)

https://doi.org/10.23919/ECC.2019.8796242

Simulation and Real-World Evaluation of Attack Detection Schemes

Matthew Porter, Arnav Joshi, Pedro Hespanhol, Anil Aswani, Matthew Johnson-Roberson, and Ram Vasudevan

In Proceedings of American Control Conference (ACC) (2019)

https://doi.org/10.23919/ACC.2019.8815318

Statistical Watermarking for Networked Control Systems

Pedro Hespanhol, Matthew Porter, Ram Vasudevan, and Anil Aswani

In Proceedings of American Control Conference (ACC) (2018)

https://doi.org/10.23919/ACC.2018.8431569

Quasi-Newton Jacobian and Hessian Updates for Pseudospectral based NMPC

Pedro Hespanhol and Rien Quirynen

In Proceedings of International Federation of Automatic Control (IFAC) (2018)

https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ifacol.2018.10.169

A Real-Time Iteration Scheme with Quasi-Newton Jacobian Updates for Nonlinear Model Predictive Control

Pedro Hespanhol and Rien Quirynen

In Proceedings of European Control Conference (ECC) (2018)

https://doi.org/10.23919/ECC.2018.8550541

Family-Personalized Dietary Planning with Temporal Dynamics

Pedro Hespanhol and Anil Aswani

In Proceedings of American Control Conference (ACC) (2018)

https://doi.org/10.23919/ACC.2018.8430885

Impact of Occupancy Modeling and Horizon Length on HVAC Controller Efficiency

Christian Garaza, Pedro Hespanhol, Yonatan Mintz, Jhoanna Rhodette Pedrasa, and Anil Aswani In Proceedings of European Control Conference (ECC) (2018)

https://doi.org/10.23919/ECC.2018.8550389

Dynamic Watermarking for General LTI Systems

Pedro Hespanhol, Matthew Porter, Ram Vasudevan, and Anil Aswani In Proceedings of Conference on Decision and Control (CDC) (2017)

https://doi.org/10.1109/CDC.2017.8263914

WORK HISTORY

University Of California Berkeley, Berkeley, CA

January 2020 - May 2020

Course Instructor

- · Lead Course Instructor of IEOR 265 Learning and Optimization (Spring 2020).

 Designed a graduate-level course which covers approximate dynamic programming, deep reinforcement learning, and learning-based model predictive control (LBMPC).
- · Course materials available on website: http://pedrohespanhol.com

UBER ATG, Pittsburgh, PA

May 2019 - August 2019

Software Engineering Intern

- · Worked on the Motion Planning team developing new optimal control algorithms and software in C++ for real-time operation of autonomous vehicles.
- · Validated methods with rigorous test cases to showcase improvement in vehicle/system performance.

Mitsubishi Electric Research Laboratories (MERL) Cambridge, MA May 2018 - August 2018

Research Intern

- · Research on mixed-integer optimization algorithms. Developed efficient mixed integer software for fast online optimal control problems, focusing on implementation in embedded platforms.
- · Developed algorithm in C and evaluated its performance on realistic optimal control problems, beating state-of-art solvers/methods across several different problems.

Mitsubishi Electric Research Laboratories (MERL) Cambridge, MA June 2017 - September 2017

Research Intern

- · Worked on research of efficient optimization algorithms tailored to solve non-linear optimal control problems, with emphasis on computational performance and solution tractability.
- · Worked on implementation in C/C++ of such algorithms in embedded platforms, focusing on rigorously analyzing computation times and memory usage of the developed methods.

Graduate Student Instructor

- · Graduate Student Instructor for IEOR 262A Math Programming I. Graduate-level course which covers linear and nonlinear optimization theory and algorithms.
- · Graduate Student Instructor for IEOR 165 Engineering Statistics, Quality Control, and Forecasting. Senior undergraduate-level course which covers classical statistical and modern machine learning techniques applied to several industrial applications.
- · Graduate Student Instructor for IEOR 151 Service Design and Operation Analysis. Senior undergraduate-level course which covers analysis and modeling of service-based systems.

PSR - Energy Consulting and Analytics Rio de Janeiro, Brazil August 2014 - August 2015 Analyst

- · Worked in development team (SDDP software): Extensive use of C/C++ and high-level mathematical modeling languages and statistical tools to improve software performance, decrease run-time, and solution output
- · Programmed optimization algorithm for HERA software: HERA is a geographical and financial analysis software to evaluate construction of hydro power-plants. HERA team won ENGIE Brazil Innovation Prize in 2015
- · Developed mathematical models and algorithms to support decision making in: energy trading, portfolio optimization, operation planning and capacity expansion in power systems

NexO Rio de Janeiro, Brazil

January 2012 to July 2013

Analyst Intern

- · Worked in development team: Implemented mathematical algorithms to optimally operate oil refineries. Work done together with CENPES (Petrobras' Research Center)
- · Developed of graphical interfaces to show refineries products flows

PRESENTATIONS AND INVITED TALKS

Surrogate Optimal Control for Strategic Multi Agent Systems

Professor S. Shankar Sastry semiautonomous group at UC Berkeley

A Structure Exploiting Branch-and-bound Algorithm For Mixed-integer Model Predictive Control

INFORMS Annual Meeting, Seattle, WA, 2019.

Statistically-Consistent Identification of Switched Linear Systems

INFORMS Annual Meeting, Seattle, WA, 2019.

Surrogate Optimal Control for Strategic Multi-Agent Systems

58th IEEE Conference on Decision and Control, Nice, France, December 11-13, 2019.

Statistical Watermarking for Networked Control Systems

Annual American Control Conference, Milwaukee, USA, June 27-29, 2018.

Newton Jacobian Updates for Nonlinear Model Predictive Control

Annual European Control Conference, Lymassol, Cyprus, June 12-15 2018.

Family-Personalized Dietary Planning with Temporal Dynamics

Annual American Control Conference, Milwaukee, USA, June 27-29, 2018.

Dynamic Watermarking for General LTI Systems

56th IEEE Conference on Decision and Control, Melbourne, Australia, December 12-15, 2017.

Deterministic Approximation Algorithm For Population-Scale Personal Dietary Management

INFORMS Computing Society Conference, Austin, TX, 2017.

Deterministic Approximation Algorithms For Population-scale Personal Dietary Management

INFORMS Annual Meeting, Nashville, TN, 2016.

HONORS AND AWARDS

Marshall-Oliver-Rosenberger Fellowship Award - granted by the Industrial Engineering and Operations Research Department at University of California Berkeley

Outstanding GSI Awards - granted by the Industrial Engineering and Operations Research Department at University of California Berkeley

Outstanding Graduate Student Instructor 2019 - granted by the Graduate Division of University of California Berkeley

ENGIE Brazil Innovation Prize - granted by ENGIE Group for the development of the HERA software.

PUC's Academic Performance Premium - granted by Pontifical Catholic University of Rio de Janeiro to students with the highest GPA.

Medal Graça Couto - granted by the Military School of Rio de Janeiro to the student with the highest academic performance of the school.

Medal Thomaz Coelho - granted by the Military School of Rio de Janeiro to the student with the highest GPU during all years during highschool.

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Computer Languages C/C++, Python, R, Matlab

Mathematical Programming Xpress, Gurobi, CPLEX, GAMS, AMPL

Machine Learning and Big Data TensorFlow, Pandas, Keras

Software and Algorithm Development

Statistical and Risk Analysis

Soft skills Communicative. Proactive leader. Problem-solver

Languages English, Portuguese, Spanish Others VBA, @Risk, Eviews, MS Office

VOLUNTEER WORK

Associação Paulo Cesar - Worked with a group of students to recover and repair computers for children in the community of Morro do Adeus in Rio de Janeiro, Brazil.